遠く離れた場所で　桜が咲いている
In a place far removed from here,
the cherry blossoms were in bloom.
We had made up our minds that
we were going to go see them.
それを見にいこうと　私たちは決めた
The cherry blossoms aren't going away.
桜は逃げない
In fact, they would be
approaching here as time passed.
むしろ　時間とともにこちらに近づいてくる
That was why we couldn't dawdle.
だから　モタモタはしていられない
A time of joy that could only come during
the winter was becoming that much shorter.
冬にしかできない幸せな時間が
それだけ短くなる
Less than two days had passed
since we came up with our plan,
計画を思い立って 2 日足らずで
私たちは旅の準備を終えた
and we were finished
getting ready for our trip.
We packed the minimum amount
that we could fit into my Cub.
荷物は私のカブに積める最低限の量
We would lodge at business
hotels and net cafés.
宿はビジネルホテルやネットカフェで済ませる
I'm off.
いってきます
Our route was still undecided.
道順は決めていない
Our destination was the farthest place
from us where they were in bloom.
目的地は　いちばん遠くで桜の咲いている所
Thanks for waiting.
お待たせ
We leave on our journey today...
私たちは今日　旅に出る
...to go and seize spring.
春をつかまえに
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
Girls.
皆さん
Please take this with you.
どうかこれを持っていってください
Komisbrot--the rye bread of soldiers.
コミスブロート
兵隊の黒パンです
お～っ
Oh...!
普通のパンより日持ちします
It will keep longer than normal bread.
Hooray! Thank you very much!
やった～ありがとうございます
Not at all.
いえいえ
Mama...
ママ
If anything happens, Koguma-san
will keep me safe, so I'll be fine.
何かあったら　小熊さんが守ってくれるから大丈夫
私に何かあったら　椎ちゃんが守ってくれる
And if anything happens to me,
Shii-chan will keep me safe.
My Super Cub will keep me safe.
スーパーカブが守ってくれる
Mm-hmm. No matter what
happens, we'll be fine.
うん！何があっても大丈夫だよ
We'll have the Super Cub along with us.
スーパーカブが一緒だから
My Hunter Cub is even stronger!
ハンターカブはもっと強い！
Well...
さて！
...it's getting to be that time.
そろそろいい時間ね
Come back safely.
いってらっしゃい
Be careful, okay?
気をつけてね
Okay.
はい
Off we go!
いってきます！
右折して韮崎から富士川沿いに南下すれば
If we turn right and head south
from Nirasaki along the Fuji River,
we should reach Shizuoka
in about three hours.
3 時間くらいで静岡
If we keep on heading along the coast,
そのまま海沿いを走れば
we could see cherry blossoms along
the Pacific coast before the day is out.
今日中に太平洋岸の桜を見られるけど
That won't do.
行きません！
もちろん！それじゃつまらない
Of course not. That wouldn't be any fun.
私たちは　いちばん遠くで春をつかまえる
We're going as far away as
we can to capture spring.
Right.
はい！
もう休憩ですか？
We're taking a break already?
We've only been at it for an hour.
まだ 1 時間くらいしか走ってないですけど
Whenever going on a long-distance trip,
どんな長距離を走るときも
あとで行動の致命的障害になるようなトラブルやその予兆は
any signs of trouble that could later
lead to critical system failure
最初の 1 時間に集中する
will come to your attention
within the first hour.
It's the devil's 60 minutes.
魔の 60 分よ
Which is why, after riding for an hour,
we stop and re-inspect each part.
だから　1 時間走ったら一度止まって　各部を再点検する
If we can ride through this
first hour without a hitch,
この 1 時間を円滑に乗り切ることができれば
そのあとの何十　何百時間をノートラブルで過ごせることが多いのよ
then the following dozens,
or even hundreds of hours,
will most commonly
come off with no trouble.
まっ　バイク乗りのおまじないのようなものね
See, it's sort of a superstition
among bikers.
そうなんだ…
Is that right?
私　甲州街道を終わりまで走ったの初めてです
This is the first time I've ever gone down
the Koshu Highway to its end.
The road keeps going. Now we have to
decide which road we're going to take.
道はまだ続く
どの道を行くか決めなくちゃいけない
We keep on this route until
the junction at Shiojiri.
このまま直進して塩尻で分岐
Then hop on National Route 19.
We pass through the mountains in Kiso,
国道 19 号線に　木曽の山中を抜けて
then follow the Chuo Main Line down.
It's the shortest route to Nagoya.
中央本線沿いを通るのが　名古屋までの最短距離
We have to at least get past
Nagoya today, don't we?
今日中に名古屋は越えないといけないんですよね？
Yes. And by following the tracks,
そう
それに線路沿いを走れば　いざというとき対処しやすい
it's easier to handle anything
that might come up.
I'd like to go up to the Sea of Japan
私は日本海に出て
and ride through the sea spray
of the surging waves along there.
怒涛の波しぶきをかぶりながら走りたいなぁ
It's hard to consider that safe.
安全とは言いかねる
Besides, there's no way
the salt air will be good
それに　塩水がプレス鉄板でできたカブの車体にいいわけがない
for the pressed steel frames on our Cubs.
Uh, I have to agree with
Koguma-san's decision.
あ… 私は小熊さんの案に賛成です
そっ　オーケー
I see. Okay, then that's what we'll do.
じゃそっちで
Huh? Are you sure?
えっ？いいの？
I can ride down any road
I want to whenever I like.
走りたい道は　いつでも好きなときに走れる
"Matsunoyasabo Coffee Shop"
中山道は　江戸時代に栄えた五街道の一つ
The Nakasendo was one of the five routes
that flourished during the Edo period.
宿場もたくさんあった
It had a lot of rest areas.
Oh, yeah?
古い茶屋のあともたくさん残っている
There are lots of old teahouses
left over from that time, too.
カフェをやるなら　見ておいて損はない
If you're going to run a café,
it couldn't hurt to have a look at them.
That explains it. So this is why
we're taking the Kiso route.
なるほど　それで木曽ルートか
Lunchtime!
お昼ごはん！
"Kiso Market"
What are we doing for lunch?
There are restaurants here.
お昼どうする？食堂あるけど
I don't want to squander any money.
無駄遣いしたくない
Huh? Are you thinking of
cooking the rice now?
ええっ！今から米といで炊く気!?
Excuse me...
あの…
Please allow me to take care of lunch.
お昼ごはんなら　私に任せてください
Thank you for waiting.
お待たせしました！
Ooh!
クリームチーズの上に
I topped it with cream cheese and
the Kiso smoked salmon I just bought.
さっき買った木曽サーモンの燻製をのせました
Please, have a taste.
どうぞ食べてみてください
Mm-hmm, delicious.
おいしい
うんまっ！ドイツかロシアの兵隊みたい！
Yum! I feel like a German
or Russian soldier!
これでエンドウ豆のベーコン添えがあれば完璧よ
Now if we had some peas and bacon,
it would be perfect.
Glad to hear it.
よかった
おいしい
"Welcome to Higashiomi City,
Shiga Prefecture"
"Roadside Station 5.1km ahead"
琵琶湖だ～！
There's Lake Biwa!
"Business Hotel Biwako Inn"
Oh, is supper ready? Let's eat!
おっ　ごはんできた？
いっただっきま～す！
You're getting the floor wet.
Go towel off and put some clothes on.
床が濡れる
体拭いて
服を着る
Aw, but curry is supposed
to be eaten naked.
あ～ん
カレーは裸で食べるものなのに～
I hear that during the summer, they hold
a meeting of Cub owners in this park.
夏には　この公園でカブオーナーのミーティングが開催されるらしい
Meeting?
ミーティング？
Over 400 different Cubs come together.
400 台以上のカブが集まるのよ
There're lots of old ones
and unusual models, too.
古いのや珍しい車種もいっぱいね
Oh, yeah?
As a Cub rider, I've always wanted
to attend one of them.
カブ乗りとしては　前から一度行ってみたいとは思ってたけど
I'd like to go, too.
私も行きたいです！
Mm-hmm.
うん
I hope summer gets here soon.
早く　夏にならないかな
The Sea of Japan doesn't seem
to have any surging waves, huh?
日本海
怒涛の波しぶき　ないですね
That's too bad.
残念
Thank goodness.
よかった
If Reiko saw any huge waves
coming in from the ocean,
大波が押し寄せる海を見たら
礼子はその場でハンターカブを売り払って
she'd be liable to sell her Hunter Cub
on the spot and buy a surfboard.
サーフボードを買ってしまうかもしれない
Huh? I was thinking you'd
be the one to do that.
はぁ？私はアンタがそうするんじゃないかと思ったわ
そんなわけない　家まで帰らなきゃいけないのに
Not a chance. I wouldn't
be able to get back home.
Besides, compared to my Cub...
それにカブより…
I wonder how much I could get for it...
いくらくらいで売れるんだろう
Huh?!
えっ!?
"Kyoto Prefecture"
"Maizuru City"
"Hyogo Prefecture"
The Tottori Sand Dunes!
鳥取砂丘だ！
"Marine Products Direct Sales Center"
"Guest House Mizuha"
Whoo, what a haul, what a haul!
ひゅ～っ　大漁大漁！
Ah, just a minute!
あっ　待ってください
え～っ
Aww...
Okay, say cheese!
はい　チーズ！
"Lake Shinji"
We're finally at the far end of Honshu.
ようやく本州の終わりまで来たわね
Amazing. Cubs really can go
anywhere in Japan, huh?
すごい…
カブって　日本のどこにでも行けるんですね
Not just Japan, either.
日本だけじゃない
They can even go across the ocean.
海だって越えられる
"Net Café Olive"
It looks like they're already starting
to bloom in Miyazaki and Kumamoto.
宮崎や熊本で　もう咲き始めてるみたいですね
We've already decided on our destination--
私たちの行く先は決まってる
the very farthest end of Japan
that our Cubs can take us.
カブで行けるギリギリ　日本の端の端
--Mm-hmm.
--Right.
うん！
はい！
We're here.
着いたわね
Right.
はい
We've caught it--spring.
つかまえた… 春を
When I said we should go
and see the cherry blossoms,
私が桜を見にいこうって言ったとき
I was sure that you were going
to say we couldn't do that.
アンタはそんなことできないって言うかと思った
I was going to. But...
そのつもりだった…
でも…
Please save me again with your Super Cub.
また… スーパーカブで助けてください
Please take this cold, dark winter...
この冷たくて暗い冬を…
...and send it...
send it away somewhere...
どこかに…
どこかに消してください！
I'm begging you...
お願いします…
お願いします！
That's...
カブに…
...not something my Cub... can do.
そんなことは… できない
I thought we should try
and see if it actually could.
本当にできないのか
確かめてみるべきだと思った
It's really nice riding
with someone, isn't it?
誰かと走るっていいですね
I always rode around by myself,
so this has been fun.
いつも一人で走り回ってたから　楽しかったです
これを持ってかえりましょう
Let's carry this back home with us.
Back to our own town.
私たちの町まで
By the day we returned,
our winterscape of a town had changed.
旅立ちの日には　冬の風景だった町は　姿を変えていた
The cherry blossoms had come out,
the sunlight shone down,
桜が咲き　陽光が降り注ぎ
and the hills and dales were
covered with fresh greenery.
野山は新緑に彩られている
At last, spring was here.
No, we had brought spring home with us.
ついに春になった
いや　春を持ち帰った
It's completely spring here, too, huh?
こっちもすっかり春ね
"Eniwa Shii"
Hello.
もしもし
Huh?
えっ
Is this Little Cub...?
このリトルカブって…
Well, um, I was going to talk
to both of you about this first,
あの… 2 人に相談しようかと思ったんですが
but when we went to look at them,
they had this one, and I bought it!
見にいったらこれがあったので　買っちゃいました！
Ho... Brand new stock.
You must be loaded, huh?
ほ～ぅ　新車在庫とか　金持ってんじゃな～い
It was a marked-down, like-new bargain,
掘り出し物の格安新古車だっていうので
so I got them to lower the price
and paid half of it myself.
必死で値切って　半分は自分で出して
I borrowed the rest from Papa,
promising to pay him back by graduation.
残りは　卒業したら絶対返すからってパパに借りました
You can ride this and continue
your Italian café project, huh?
これに乗って　イタリア化計画を続けるわけね
Mm-hmm!
うん！
With a Cub, I can go shopping anywhere.
カブがあれば　どこにでも買い物に行けるし
Riding a motorbike
in the spring feels good.
春はバイクで走るのが気持ちいい
That's why there are more
of them on the roads.
だから道にバイクが増える
You have to be careful.
気をつけないといけない
Then comes summer.
それから夏
It's not true what they say
about riding making it cooler,
バイクで走ってれば　涼しいだなんてウソだから
so if you're not careful,
you can get so hot you collapse.
気を抜いてると　ぶっ倒れるくらい暑いわよ
Then comes autumn, and winter again.
Winters are cold and long...
すぐに秋がきて冬になる
冬は寒いし長い…
I have no parents. No money, either.
親はいない
お金もない
Nor do I have any hobbies, friends,
or goals for the future.
友達も趣味も　将来の目標もない
But my days of nothingness
have changed just a little.
何もなかった私の毎日が　少しだけ変わった
Was it because I came across my Cub?
それは　カブと出会えたから？
No.
違う
If you sit back and do nothing,
a Cub won't help you.
黙っていても　カブは助けてくれない
You probably have to have
a desire of your own.
たぶん　自分で何かを望まないと
Like, say... wanting to turn at an unfamiliar
corner you've never turned at before.
例えば
いつもは行くことのない　知らない角を曲がってみたい
It doesn't have to be
any bigger than that.
そんな小さなことでいい
When you do, I'm sure
the Cub will respond.
そうすればきっとカブは　応えてくれる
It isn't a magical, do-anything machine.
なんでもできる魔法の機械じゃない
けど　困難に立ち向かい
But when you have to face a hurdle,
or come through with something...
何かを成し遂げようとしたとき
...it will definitely be there at your side.
きっと味方になってくれる
Such were our Super Cubs.
それが私たちのスーパーカブ
I'm going to keep riding
forever... on my...
どこまでも走ろう
この　スーパーカブで
"Episode 12"
"Super Cub"
...Super Cub.
"Episode 12"
"Super Cub"
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ